I recently watched this data fetching
video by Josh and I was shocked how bad
the advice was if every single website
implemented what he said to do 50% of
the entire world would no longer be able
to access the internet so in this video
I'm going to be talking about what is
wrong with his advice as well as showing
what you can do instead to solve the
problem he was trying to
fix welcome back to web dev simplified
my name is Kyle and my job is to
simplify the web for you so you can
start building your dream project sooner
and in J's video the problem he was
trying to solve is when you're
requesting data from a server if the
server is really slow what do you do to
let the user know in our case when I
click this load users button you can see
our data loaded almost instantaneously
as you can see I have an API set up and
I have the delay set to 10 milliseconds
so as you can see it's a very quick data
Fetch and that's because I have fast
internet I'm hardwired in and all of
that what happens if there is a problem
with the server and the server was
taking longer than usual to respond
because there's too many requests coming
in let's say instead of 10 millisecond
this actually was taking 10 seconds so
if we restart our server and I just
refresh this page and I click load users
you're now going to notice it's stuck in
this loading State and it's going to be
stuck there for 10 seconds which is
obviously not a good user experience I
may think that your site is broken and I
may leave because I'm like what the heck
there's a problem with your site
eventually the data gets there but it
takes a really long time what Josh
proposed that you do to solve this
problem is inside of your code where
you're fetching out your user
information this is pretty much a basic
fetch request where we're just setting
our loading State then we're getting our
dat setting it to success if we have an
error we set it to an error and that's
all that's happening but inside of here
we're setting a timeout this is Josh's
idea is that if your request takes too
long in our example we're just saying 2
seconds if it takes longer than 2
seconds just cancel the request
completely because there's probably
something wrong with your server so now
you can see if I save that refresh and
click load it's going to wait 2 seconds
and then I'm going to get an error
because this timeout ran it canceled my
request and it went into this catch
block right here with an error now
technically doing this will solve the
problem that we came into where we have
extra long loading states that are
probably a problem with our server but
the problem that this introduces is that
now if you're on a slow connection for
example if you have really bad data
connection I'm very used to this living
in Nebraska it's like the whole for all
data connection Maps but if you have
really slow data connection or you just
have a slow internet connection in
general you're going to hit this 2C
timeout and you're not going to be able
to access data at all and a large
portion of the world is living on 3G or
slower data so it's always going to take
them longer than 2 3 4 seconds to
request data from the server which means
they're never going to be able to access
anything cuz it's just airing out before
the data ever gets there now I love
Josh's videos I think he does a really
good job but unfortunately in this
regard I think he kind of dropped the
ball and it's perfectly okay he was
solving a problem and he solved it he
just didn't really think about some of
the edge cases so I want to show you an
alternative solution that does the exact
same thing of solving the problem but
doesn't ever degrade the experience for
anyone else so the easiest thing by far
that we can do is instead of canceling
our request here instead we just want to
notify the user that there is some type
of delay going on so instead of
canceling the request we're going to
remove this canceling code I'm just
going to comment it out for now we'll
comment this out and we'll comment out
the section where we're adding in the
signal for cancelling that's all of our
cancel code removed and instead when the
request is taking too long to get back
to us I'm going to set a new fetch
status and this one I'm going to set to
delayed saying that this response is
delayed compared to what we expect it
shouldn't be taking this long and this
may be 2 seconds 3 seconds 4 seconds 5
seconds it's whatever your app needs so
now we can actually take that delay
response come in here and when our fetch
status is equal to to delayed we can
actually render out a message to our
users so let's just render out a div
that says this response is taking longer
than normal that looks pretty good and
up here just to make sure our button is
properly disabled because we still want
it to be disabled when our fetch status
is equal to delayed we're just going to
add that in like this so now I'm going
to click on load users you can see it's
loading and after a couple seconds you
can now see it says hey this response is
taking longer than normal but it's still
processing my response in the background
and after that full 10-second delay I
will see the data show up just like you
saw and now I can click the button again
or do whatever else I want so I'm
getting the Best of Both Worlds when I
click this button and the data is taking
too long to get back to me I'm giving
the user a message saying hey there's
probably something wrong with our server
this is why it's taking longer than
normal you know this is perfectly normal
don't worry about it we're still working
on this but for the slower browsers you
can see we're still getting that data
back instead of just canceling out of
the response completely we can even take
this a step further by actually adding
in like a cancel button so what we can
do inside here this response is taking
longer than normal it is still running
in the background if you want you can
cancel the request and rryy it obviously
you can use whatever normal copy you
want but inside here I'm just going to
add a cancel button so let's just come
in here make sure I have this fragment
to close everything off and we'll add in
a button and this button will say cancel
just like that so now if I click load
users after 2 seconds you will see that
this cancel button will pop up and I can
click on it but I need to make it
actually cancel my request so to do that
I'm going to create my abort controller
here just like I was before I want to
pass along my signal so I can actually
cancel my request but instead of
canceling it in this timeout i instead
want to cancel it down here when I click
on this button so on click I want to run
some code that's going to essentially
call controller. abort now in order to
get this controller to abort things I
need to store it inside of a reference
so we can just say here const controller
ref is equal to use ref and then we can
say our controller ref urrent is equal
to that and here our controller ref.
current. signal and down here controller
ref. current. abort so now all this is
saying is that we can abort the request
directly from inside of here so now if I
click load users you can see after 2
seconds I get this message and if I
click cancel you can see it cancels
everything out and gives me back this
error response if I want I can even come
in here and I can say if e.name is equal
to abort
controller well then I can set my fet
fetch stus to something like
canceled or we'll just say canel there
we go otherwise I'll set it to error
because this is going to be called
anytime I actually cancel it with an
abort request it's going to come into
this code and then I could you know just
copy this we'll say if it's
cancelled canell we'll just render out
the text cancelled
instead there we go so now if I click
load users you can see it's waiting
after 2 seconds I'll get this message
when I click cancel you can see that my
error is incorrect and that's because
that this instead of saying abort
controller should say abort error that
was just a type on my end so now let's
click load user you can see it's loading
I'm going to get this cancel and now you
can see it say canceled right here now I
don't want this video to be an attack on
Josh or anything like that I think his
content is really great I'll actually
put a link to his channel on the screen
so you can check out some of his other
videos I just saw this recent video and
I had to make a response to it because I
really didn't like the advice being
shown there and I wanted to show you
guys a way to do the exact same thing
he's trying to solve but in a much
better way